Is being overweight um a risk factor for
being hippogonado as well?
>> Yes, it is. Um especially if well we now
know there's a few different types of
obesity. The most common type, the one
that accompanies aging is where not only
do you as you age you lose muscle mass,
you lose skeletal muscle and you you
gain subcutaneous fat. And we see that,
you know, our pinchable fat, our faces
get fatter, our necks sag, whatever.
That's a problem. But the biggest
problem is you gain fat around your
internal organs called visceral fat.
Visceral fat is an endocrine organ.
Actually, it secretes chemicals into
your bloodstream that can cause a
chronic low-grade inflammatory state.
And when you have obesity plus this
chronic inflammation caused by the
obesity at least directly or indirectly
that's what we call metabolic syndrome
and a huge percentage of people in the
US have metabolic syndrome and now I'm
forgetting what the original question
was because I'm I'm going off on my
lecture
>> if being obese was the risk factor for
low tea as well.
>> Yes. So what happens is when you have
metabolic syndrome and you're obese,
this chronic inflammation interferes
with your testosterone production
sometimes directly. For example, some of
the chemicals released by visceral fat
which are called atypoccytoines
uh have a pro-inflammatory effect on
parts of the brain. for example, um your
hypothalamus, which releases something
called G&RH, which tells your um
pituitary to produce other hormones
called LH and FSH. The LH and FSH
obviously tell your testes to make
testosterone.
And um the inflammatory state of obesity
can actually interfere directly with
that circuit at multiple different
points. But increasingly what we're also
finding out is not only does
in when I use the term obesity what I
mean is metabolic syndrome because I
said there's different types of obesity
but okay so we're also finding out is
obesity is also accompanied by something
by this chronic inflammatory state that
can interfere with your androgen
signaling is what it looks like too. So,
you can have a situation where men have
so-called normal levels, but their
androgen signaling is very inefficient
for multiple cellular reasons, mostly
mitochondrial reasons. Um, if people
don't know what mitochondria are,
they're the little they're parts of just
about every cell in your body that
generate energy. And a big part of the
way that testosterone works is by
modulating those. But you can think of
them as engines. Okay. Um and it does so
in beneficial ways. It can do so in
certain contexts in not so beneficial
ways. But yeah, the answer to the
question is does obesity predispose you
to low testosterone? Yes. Not only does
it predispose you to having low
testosterone levels, it predisposes you
to having, for lack of a better term,
um, a situation where your testosterone
doesn't work as efficiently
uh, as it should, if that makes sense.
>> Yeah. And concerning treatment of those
guys, will putting them on TRT help with
the obesity or will you first make them
lose weight so it will help for the
testosterone?
>> So when you when you say those guys, you
do you mean just specifically obese guys
or obese guys with with normal?
>> Yeah. Obese guys with with low tea
already?
>> Oh, with low tea already. Yes. So there
Yeah, there's multiple studies that show
this too. The testosterone helps in in
many ways. The first way, the way that's
probably most relevant to the audiences.
What are the most common drugs used to
treat obesity these days? Well, that
would be things like simaglutide,
tzapatide. Some people use retatride,
which is not, you know, approved in the
US yet. Um, those drugs are pretty
effective, right? The problem is they
cause a lot of muscle loss because
people end up losing a lot of fat and
but they lose a lot of muscle. If you
lose a lot of muscle when you when
you're losing weight, that's not good
because it it actually lowers your
resting metabolic rate to lose muscle
tissue. Uh most of your glucose is
actually glucose being blood sugar is
utilized by your skeletal muscle. So the
idea is if you're obese, yes, you want
to lose fat, but you want to lose fat
without losing muscle. So the TRT does
several things in addition to like drugs
like GLP1 drugs is it helps preserve
muscle mass while you lose fat. It also
accelerates the fat loss because
testosterone has very potent effects on
pathways that affect lipogenesis and um
you know handling of blood sugar and
insulin sensitivity especially. So, what
I would say is yes, it does almost
always help. And and and in men,
especially with low testosterone levels,
it it it's h pretty profound.
>> So, you you don't make them lose weight
first and you you say TRT will be the
cherry on top. You you start them on TRT
at once.
>> What I do is I start them on four
things. First thing is resistance
training.
Some type of weightlifting is extremely
important. The second thing is yes,
diet, but especially we want to have a
protein intake that's targeted towards
muscle gain. Then the third thing we do
is something targeted towards the
obesity which is in the vast majority of
cases saglletide there's appetite
whatever and then you know if I think
it's been going to be beneficial in many
cases it is then the testosterone comes
on top of all those things one thing I
don't do is I don't put people on TRT if
they're not willing to to do the at
least the resistance training and the
diet modification okay just being fat
and being on TRT tea and just sitting on
your couch is is going to be
I guess if your testosterone levels are
very low you may have some like
cognitive benefits from it but medically
speaking you're not going to benefit
anywhere near as much from it and there
are many studies the most famous one is
something called the T4DM study which
was published in the Lancet I believe in
2021 or 2022
and this study showed that even in men
with normal pre-treat treatment
testosterone levels on the lower side
but still fall within the normal range.
If they do a resistance training program
plus testosterone
compared to men who do just resistance
training and no testosterone, they have
about a 40% decreased risk of developing
type 2 diabetes,
>> which is actually higher
which is actually a higher rate of
there's probably a better term for this,
but a higher rate of not getting
diabetes than if you use the diabetes
drug called metformin. So metformin is
commonly used in patients at risk of
diabetes to prevent them from getting
diabetes. There's a few studies now that
show that TRT actually works at least as
good as metformin, probably even better.
And how does it work? Number one, it
increases your skeletal muscle mass,
which is what helps with the glucose
control longterm. That's not a shortterm
effect of TRT.
And it also reduces your visceral fat.
Remember when I was talking about the
fat around your internal organs,
visceral fat? There's very few drugs
that reduce that. GLP-1 drugs looks like
they can reduce it. But we've known for
a while that testosterone also reduces
visceral fat. And it's very interesting
how testosterone does that because it
involves estradiol.
Okay, which a lot of guys are a little
bit confused about. But yeah, that's uh
essentially the answer.